<dw-document xmlns:dw="http://www.ibm.com/developerWorks/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" local-site="worldwide" version="v18" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../schema/dw-document-8.0.xsd"><dw-article auto-number="no" layout="ArticleStandard18" skill-level="2" toc="auto"><id cma-id="1035508" original="yes"/><keywords content="blockchain, intro, basics, hyperledger project, distributed ledger,             dlt, distributed ledger technology,              sloane brakeville, bhargav perepa, ibm, cloud, service"/><meta-last-updated day="22" initials="gemoore@us.ibm.com" month="06" year="2018"/><!--https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-blockchain-basics-intro-bluemix-trs/--><!--cl-blockchain-basics-intro-bluemix-trs-_-article--><!--000 no refs to the bluemix catalog on this article, unless I update any of the
        CTA bars--><content-area-primary name="blockchain"/><content-area-secondary name="cloud"/><title>Blockchain basics: Introduction to distributed ledgers</title><subtitle>Get to know this game-changing technology and how to start using
            it</subtitle><target-content-file file-description="Blockchain 101 infographic" file-type="pdf" filename="What it is, how it works" link-method-dd="no" link-method-ftp="no" link-method-http="yes" registration-required="no" show-license="no" size="705KB" target-content-type="Product documentation" url-download-director="" url-ftp="" url-http="https://www-01.ibm.com/common/ssi/cgi-bin/ssialias?htmlfid=XI912346USEN"/><pdf pages="8" paperSize="common" size="206 KB" url="cl-blockchain-basics-intro-bluemix-trs-pdf.pdf"/><author email="sbrakev@us.ibm.com" email-cc="" jobtitle="Blockchain Specialist at IBM" publish-email="yes"><author-level>none</author-level><bio><nbsp/></bio><img align="left" alt="Author photo - Sloane Brakeville" height="60" src="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/p-sbrakeville60.jpg" valign="top" width="60"/><author-name><GivenName>Sloane</GivenName><FamilyName>Brakeville</FamilyName></author-name><company-name> IBM</company-name><social-networks><social-network><social-network-name>LinkedIn</social-network-name><social-network-url>https://www.linkedin.com/in/sbrakev</social-network-url></social-network></social-networks></author><author email="bvperepa@us.ibm.com" email-cc="" jobtitle="WebSphere Integration Technology Specialist" publish-email="yes"><author-level>contributing-author</author-level><bio><b>Bhargav Perepa</b> is a WebSphere IT Specialist with IBM Federal Software Group in Washington D.C. He was a WebSphere developer at the IBM Austin WebSphere Development Lab and has previous Smalltalk and C++ development experience. Bhargav holds a Masters degree in Computer Sciences from IIT, Chicago and an MBA degree from UT-Austin, Texas.  You can reach Bhargav at <a href="mailto:bvperepa@us.ibm.com">bvperepa@us.ibm.com</a>.</bio><img align="left" alt="Photo of Bhargav Perepa" border="0" height="60" name="Bhargav Perepa" src="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/p-bperepa.jpg" valign="top" width="60"/><author-name><GivenName>Bhargav</GivenName><FamilyName>Perepa</FamilyName></author-name><company-name>IBM</company-name><social-networks><social-network><social-network-name>LinkedIn</social-network-name><social-network-url>https://www.linkedin.com/in/bhargav-perepa/</social-network-url></social-network></social-networks></author><!--<date-published day="09" month="05" year="2016"/>
        <date-updated day="18" month="03" year="2018"/>--><date-published day="18" month="03" year="2018"/><social-media-meta><twitter-summary-card><twitter-card-title>IBM Blockchain basics: Introduction to distributed
                    ledgers</twitter-card-title><twitter-card-abstract>Learn how blockchain networks are transforming the
                    way business transactions happen.  And see how IBM is helping to advance the
                    technology.</twitter-card-abstract><twitter-card-img height="440" src="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/twitterdw-28828-serverledger.png" width="880"/></twitter-summary-card></social-media-meta><abstract>Everyone is placing bets on how the blockchain technology will
            revolutionize the way organizations and institutions transact business. Let's
            look at how a blockchain network operates, how you can take advantage of it,
            and how IBM is helping to advance the technology.</abstract><docbody><p>Everyone is watching how blockchain's distributed ledger technology is revolutionizing the way
                organizations conduct
                their business transactions. </p><button-link><text>Kick-start your exploration of distributed ledger technology with the new IBM
                    Blockchain Platform Starter Plan</text><url>http://www.ibm.com/blockchain/getting-started.html</url></button-link><p>Let's look at how a blockchain network operates,
                how you can take advantage of it, and how IBM and other companies are
                collaborating to advance the technology across a spectrum of industries.
                First, a little background is in order.</p><heading refname="" type="h2">What is a distributed ledger?</heading><p> A <strong><em>distributed ledger</em></strong> is a type of database that
                is shared, replicated, and synchronized among the members of a
                decentralized network.
                The distributed ledger records the transactions, such as the exchange of
                assets or data, among the participants in the network.</p><p> Participants in the network govern and agree by consensus on the updates
                to the records in the ledger. No central authority or third-party mediator, such as a
                financial institution or clearinghouse, is involved. Every record in the distributed ledger 
                has a timestamp and unique
                cryptographic signature, thus making the ledger an auditable, immutable
                history of all transactions in the network.
                <!--One implementation of distributed ledger
                technology is the open source Hyperledger Fabric blockchain.--></p><heading refname="" type="h3">The role of business ledgers</heading><p>In today's connected and integrated world, economic
                activity<!--, wealth and
                value creation--> takes place in
                business networks that span <!--across--> national, geographic, and
                jurisdictional boundaries. Business networks typically come together at
                marketplaces where the <em><strong>participants</strong></em>, such as
                producers, consumers, suppliers, partners, market makers/enablers, and
                other stakeholders own, control, and exercise their rights, privileges,
                and entitlements on objects of value known as
                    <em><strong>assets</strong></em>.</p><p>Assets can be tangible and physical, such as cars, homes, or strawberries,
                or intangible and virtual, such as deeds, patents, and stock certificates.
                Asset ownership and transfers are the
                    <em><strong>transactions</strong></em> that create value in a business
                network.</p><p>Transactions typically involve various participants like buyers, sellers,
                and intermediaries (such as banks, auditors, or notaries) whose business
                agreements and contracts <!--within a business context and--> are recorded
                in <em><strong>ledgers</strong></em>. A business typically uses multiple
                ledgers to keep track of asset ownership and asset transfers between
                participants in its various lines of businesses. Ledgers are the systems
                of record for a business's economic activities and interests.</p><p>A typical ledger looks something like this:</p><figure><img alt="" height="190" src="ledger.png" width="639"/></figure><heading refname="" type="h3">Problems with current business ledgers</heading><p>Current business ledgers in use today are deficient in many ways. They are
                inefficient, costly, and <!--slow,--> subject to misuse and tampering.
                <!--These problems stem from reliance on centralized third-party <!-\-actors-\->
                systems, such as financial institutions, clearinghouses, and other
                mediators of existing institutional arrangements.</p>
            <p>These centralized ledger systems lead to bottlenecks and slowdowns of
                transaction settlements. --> Lack of transparency, as well as susceptibility
                to corruption and fraud, lead to disputes. Having to resolve disputes and
                possibly reverse transactions or provide insurance for transactions is
                costly. These risks and uncertainties contribute to missed business
                opportunities.</p><p>Furthermore, out-of-sync copies of business ledgers on each network
                participant’s own systems lead to faulty business decisions made on
                temporary, incorrect data. At best, the ability to make a fully informed
                decision is delayed while differing copies of the ledgers are
                reconciled.</p><!--<pullquote>
                <pullquote-text>What is unique about a blockchain network is its
                    decentralized consensus mechanism.</pullquote-text>
                <pullquote-source/>
            </pullquote>--><heading refname="" type="h2">What is blockchain, exactly?</heading><!--<sidebar>
                <p><strong>Blockchain terms and use cases</strong></p>
                <p>Get a handle on more blockchain terminology and all its potential uses
                    in our "<a target="new"
                        href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-blockchain-basics-glossary-bluemix-trs/index.html"
                        >Blockchain glossary</a>."</p>
            </sidebar>--><sidebar><p><strong>Now, could you explain "blockchain" to someone?</strong></p><p>If you hesitated, you're not alone! Our <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/dwblog/2017/what-is-blockchain-hyperledger-fabric-distributed-ledger/" target="new">Blockchain primer</a> really breaks it down. Read it
                    and you'll be ready to regale your family, neighbors, and co-workers
                    with your new-found fluency!</p></sidebar><p>A blockchain is a tamper-evident, shared digital ledger that records
                transactions in a public or private peer-to-peer network. Distributed to
                all member nodes in the network, the ledger permanently records, in a
                sequential chain of cryptographic hash-linked
                    <em><strong>blocks</strong></em>, the history of asset exchanges that
                take place between the peers in the network.</p><p>All the confirmed and validated transaction blocks are linked and chained
                from the beginning of the chain to the most current block, hence the name
                        <em><strong>blockchain</strong></em>. The blockchain thus acts as
                a single source of truth, and members in a blockchain network can view
                only those transactions that are relevant to them.</p><heading refname="" type="h2">How does a blockchain network work?</heading><sidebar><heading>Test your blockchain knowledge!</heading><p>Take the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/courses/all/blockchain-essentials/">Blockchain essentials course for developers</a>, and you'll learn
                    the ins and outs of asset transfers. At the end of the free,
                    self-paced course, take a quiz, get a badge, and start planning useful
                    blockchain applications for your business network.</p></sidebar><p>Instead of relying on a third party, such as a financial institution, to
                mediate transactions, member nodes in a blockchain network
                <!--payment system--> use a consensus protocol to agree on ledger content,
                and cryptographic hashes and digital signatures to ensure the integrity of
                transactions.</p><p><em><strong>Consensus</strong></em> ensures that the shared ledgers are
                exact copies, and lowers the risk of fraudulent transactions, because
                tampering would have to occur across many places at exactly the same time.
                        <strong><em>Cryptographic hashes</em></strong>, such as the SHA256
                computational algorithm, ensure that any alteration to transaction input
                <mdash/> even the most minuscule change <mdash/> results in a different
                hash value being computed, which indicates potentially compromised
                transaction input. <strong><em>Digital signatures</em></strong> ensure
                that transactions originated from senders (signed with private keys) and
                not imposters.</p><p>The decentralized peer-to-peer blockchain network prevents any single
                participant or group of participants from controlling the underlying
                infrastructure or undermining the entire system. Participants in the
                network are all equal, adhering to the same protocols. They can be
                individuals, state actors, organizations, or a combination of all these
                types of participants.</p><p>At its core, the system records the chronological order of transactions
                with all nodes agreeing to the validity of transactions using the chosen
                consensus model. The result is transactions that cannot be altered or
                reversed, unless the change is agreed to by all members in the network in
                a subsequent transaction.</p><button-link><text>Kick-start your own blockchain network now with the new IBM
                    Blockchain Platform Starter Plan</text><url>http://www.ibm.com/blockchain/getting-started.html</url></button-link><heading refname="" type="h2">What are the business benefits of
                blockchain?</heading><!--<sidebar> 
                <img align="left" alt="Blockchain newsletter signup" height="75"
                    src="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/newsletter-icon-blockchain.png"
                    width="75"/>
                <p>Get a monthly roundup of the best free tools, training, and community
                    resources to put Blockchain to work.<br/><a
                        href="http://ibm.biz/blockchain-newsletter" target="new"
                            ><strong>Current issue</strong></a> | <a
                        href="http://ibm.biz/blockchain-newsletter-signup" target="new"
                            ><strong>Subscribe</strong></a></p>
            </sidebar>--><p>In legacy business networks, all participants maintain their own ledgers
                with duplication and discrepancies that result in disputes, increased
                settlement times, and the need for intermediaries with their associated
                overhead costs. However, by using blockchain-based shared ledgers, where
                transactions cannot be altered once validated by consensus and written to
                the ledger, businesses can <strong><em>save time and costs while reducing
                        risks</em></strong>. </p><p>Blockchain consensus mechanisms provide the benefits of a consolidated,
                consistent dataset with reduced errors, near-real-time reference data, and
                the flexibility for participants to change the descriptions of the assets
                they own.</p><p>Because no one participating member owns the source of origin for
                information contained in the shared ledger, blockchain technologies lead
                to increased trust and integrity in the flow of transaction information
                among the participating members.</p><p>Immutability mechanisms of blockchain technologies lead to lowered cost of
                audit and regulatory compliance with improved transparency. And because
                contracts being executed on business networks using blockchain
                technologies are automated and final, businesses benefit from increased
                speed of execution, reduced costs, and less risk, all of which enables
                businesses to <strong><em>build new revenue streams to interact with
                        clients</em></strong>.</p><heading type="h2">What's a good blockchain use case?</heading><sidebar><heading>Is blockchain is right for you?</heading><!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RKb3D66Akv4--><video-container><video-id>RKb3D66Akv4</video-id><video-title display="no">What makes a good blockchain
                        solution?</video-title><video-length><minutes>02</minutes><seconds>31</seconds></video-length></video-container></sidebar><p>Blockchain was first introduced to the market as the 
                <a href="https://www.ibm.com/blogs/blockchain/2017/05/the-difference-between-bitcoin-and-blockchain-for-business/">technology
                underpinning Bitcoin exchanges</a>, but its practical uses in the world of
                business extend far beyond cryptocurrency transactions. For example, in
                finance, blockchain networks allow securities trades to be settled in
                minutes rather than days. In supply chains, blockchain networks allow the
                flow of goods and payments to be tracked and logged in real time.</p><p>To determine whether your use case is a good fit for blockchain, ask
                yourself these questions:</p><ol><li>Is a business network involved?</li><li>Is consensus used to validate transactions?</li><li>Is an audit trail, or provenance, required?</li><li>Must the record of transactions be immutable, or tamper proof?</li><li><!--Finality (less disputes)-->Should dispute resolution be
                    final?</li></ol><p>If you answered yes to the first question and to at least one other, then
                your use case would benefit from blockchain technology. A network always
                needs to be involved for blockchain to be the right solution, but the
                network can take many forms. The network can be <em>between
                    organizations</em>, such as a supply chain, or the network can be
                    <em>within an organization</em>. Within an organization, a blockchain
                network could be used to share reference data between divisions or to
                create an audit or compliance network, for example. The network can also
                exist <em>between individuals</em>, who might need to store data, digital
                assets, or contracts on the blockchain, for example.</p><p>See <a href="https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/industries/">industry
                    examples</a> of how diverse organizations <mdash/> in banking and financial
                markets, supply chain, healthcare, and transportation, for
                example <mdash/> are adopting blockchain to support new business
                models.</p><heading type="h2">What is Hyperledger?</heading><!--<sidebar>
                <heading>How to develop your first Hyperleder Fabric blockchain app,
                    fast!</heading>
                <p>Choose your preferred development environment: online, local, or in the
                    cloud!</p>
                <p>Start with online samples. Develop and test locally in a complete dev
                    environment. Share your blockchain app for collaborative development
                    on the IBM Cloud.</p>
                <p><a href="https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/getting-started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow"><strong>Develop
                            your blockchain app</strong></a></p>
            </sidebar>--><p><a href="http://www.hyperledger.org">Hyperledger</a> is an open source
                effort to advance cross-industry blockchain technologies for business use.
                It's a global collaboration, hosted by The Linux Foundation<reg/>, including
                leaders in finance, banking, Internet of Things, supply chain,
                manufacturing, and technology. These 183+ diverse members and 9 ongoing
                projects, including Hyperledger Fabric and Hyperledger Composer, work in
                concert to create an open, standardized, and enterprise-grade distributed
                ledger framework and code base.</p><p>The <a href="IBM Blockchain: From farm to table">Hyperledger Fabric</a> framework supports distributed
                ledger solutions on permissioned networks, where the members are known to
                each other, for a wide range of industries.
                Its modular architecture maximizes the confidentiality, resilience, and
                flexibility of blockchain solutions. <a href="https://www.hyperledger.org/projects/fabric">Hyperledger
                    Composer</a> is a set of free, open source tools for quickly
                prototyping, defining, and testing a Hyperledger Fabric blockchain network and writing
                applications to interact with it.</p><p>The IBM Blockchain Platform runs on the Hyperledger Fabric framework and
                integrates the Hyperledger Composer toolset as the "IBM Blockchain
                Platform: Develop" tools. 
                Learn more about <a href="https://www.hyperledger.org/projects/fabric" target="new">Hyperledger Fabric</a> and the <a href="http://www.ibm.com/blockchain/platform/">IBM Blockchain
                    Platform</a>.</p><!-- <p>To provide functionality and required capabilities, the Hyperledger Fabric
                is based on these concepts:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Smart contracts</li>
                <li>Digital assets</li>
                <li>System of record repositories/stores</li>
                <li>Decentralized consensus-based network</li>
                <li>Pluggable consensus algorithms/models</li>
                <li>Cryptographic security</li>
            </ul>--><!--<figure>
                <img alt="Reference architecture" height="342" src="fig8.png" width="550"
                />
            </figure>--><!--<p>You can learn more at the <a href="http://www.hyperledger.org">Hyperledger
                    Project</a>, in the <a target="new"
                    href="http://www.the-blockchain.com/docs/Hyperledger%20Whitepaper.pdf"
                    >Hyperledger Whitepaper</a>, and in the <a target="new"
                    href="http://hyperledger-fabric.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">Hyperledger
                    Fabric documentation</a> on GitHub.</p>--><heading type="h3"><!--IBM and Hyperledger-->Enterprise blockchain
                requirements</heading><sidebar><heading>IBM's perspective on blockchain technology</heading><!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PzvfSZEid0Q--><video-container><video-id>PzvfSZEid0Q</video-id><video-title display="no">IBM's point of view on blockchain
                        technology</video-title><video-length><minutes>09</minutes><seconds>02</seconds></video-length></video-container></sidebar><p>We believe that blockchain is a truly disruptive technology that can
                transform business networks. We also believe that this innovation has to
                happen in the open, collaborating with other technology companies and
                industries. To this end, IBM continues to contribute code to several
                active Hyperledger projects. </p><p>From IBM's perspective, industrial-grade blockchain technologies have the
                following characteristics:</p><ul><li>A <strong>shared, permissioned ledger</strong> is the append-only
                    system of record (SOR) and single source of truth. It is visible to
                    the authenticated members in the business network channels.</li><li>A <strong>consensus protocol</strong> agreed to by all participating
                    members of the business network ensures that the ledger is updated
                    only with network-verified transactions.</li><li><strong>Cryptography</strong> ensures tamper-proof security,
                    authentication, and integrity of transactions.
                    <!--being recorded in shared ledgerTamper-proof security--></li><!--<li>Privacy with the identity of participants not linked to transactions</li>
                <li>Scalability <!-\-000 ??? with proven IBM record-\-></li>
                <li>Confidentiality with permission control</li>
                <li>Auditability and audit transparency (identity
                    and ownership are proven at any point of the transaction lifecycle)</li>--><li><strong>Chaincode</strong> (also called mart contracts) encapsulates
                    participant terms of agreement for the business that takes place on
                    the network; chaincode is stored on the validating peer nodes in the blockchain.</li></ul><p>In addition to these attributes, enterprise blockchain technology needs to
                meet key industry requirements such as performance, verified identifies,
                and private and confidential transactions. Hyperledger Fabric has been
                architected to meet these needs. It is also designed with a pluggable
                consensus model, allowing businesses to select an optimal algorithm for
                their networks.</p><heading type="h2">How do I get started?</heading><!--<sidebar>
                <heading>Ready to start developing your own blockchain
                    solutions?</heading>
                <p>For the fastest start to developing your first blockchain application,
                    head over to the <a
                        href="https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/getting-started">IBM Blockchain
                        Platform page for developers</a>.</p>
                <p>When you're ready to dig deeper into deploying blockchain network
                    solutions, examine all your options in <a
                        href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-ibm-blockchain-101-quick-start-guide-for-developers-bluemix-trs/index.html"
                        target="new">IBM Blockchain 101: Quick-start guide for
                        developers</a>.</p>
            </sidebar>--><!--000 added this paragraph 4.30.17 from a press release: 
                https://www-03.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/52192.wss--><!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UW5Ex8oZ7eQ--><!--<sidebar>
                <heading>IBM Blockchain: From farm to table</heading>
                <!-\-https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UW5Ex8oZ7eQ-\->
                <video-container>
                    <video-id>UW5Ex8oZ7eQ</video-id>
                    <video-title display="no">IBM Blockchain: From farm to table</video-title>
                    <video-length>
                        <!-\-<minutes>0.0</minutes>-\->
                        <seconds>15</seconds>
                    </video-length>
                </video-container>
            </sidebar>--><p>IBM is the leader in secure open-source blockchain solutions built for the
                enterprise. As an early member of the Linux Foundation's Hyperledger
                Project, IBM is dedicated to supporting the development of openly governed
                blockchains. IBM has worked with over 400 clients across financial
                services, supply chains, IoT, risk management, digital rights management,
                and healthcare to implement blockchain applications delivered via the IBM
                Cloud.</p><p>IBM offers a flexible platform and secure infrastructure to help you
                develop, govern, and operate your enterprise blockchain network. 
                Over 40 active networks with multiple organizations 
                are using the IBM Blockchain Platform to exchange
                assets every day and improve business processes ranging from food safety
                to trade efficiencies and digital payments. Learn about <a href="https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/offerings.html">IBM Blockchain
                    solutions</a>, and see how you can <a href="https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/getting-started.html" target="new">start using blockchain in your business</a> today.</p><p>If you're a developer, the easiest, most economical way to learn your way around a real business
                blockchain and start developing blockchain skills <em>and</em> applications
                now is to sign up for the IBM Blockchain Platform Starter Plan. 
                With the new Starter Plan, you can
                    quickly spin up a blockchain pre-production network, deploy sample applications, 
            and develop and deploy client applications.</p><button-link><text>Accelerate your blockchain development skills with the new IBM
                    Blockchain Platform Starter Plan</text><url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-ibm-blockchain-101-quick-start-guide-for-developers-bluemix-trs/index.html</url></button-link><!-- <heading refname="" type="h3">IBM Blockchain on IBM Cloud</heading>
            <figure>
                <img alt="Blockchain service page in IBM Cloud" height="128"
                    src="IBM_Blockchain_logo_128sq.png" width="129"/>
            </figure>
            <p>With the <a target="new"
                    href="https://console.ng.bluemix.net/catalog/services/blockchain/?ca=dw-_-bluemix-_-cl-blockchain-basics-intro-bluemix-trs-_-article"
                    >IBM Blockchain Platform on IBM Cloud</a>,
                you can create your own blockchain network with validating nodes and a
                security service. From there, you can deploy smart contracts (also called
                chaincode), see results, and build applications.</p>
            
            <p>Experiment with <a target="new"
                    href="https://console.ng.bluemix.net/docs/services/blockchain/index.html?ca=dw-_-bluemix-_-cl-blockchain-basics-intro-bluemix-trs-_-article"
                    >Blockchain on IBM Cloud</a>. Follow the step-by-step instructions in <a
                    target="new"
                    href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-ibm-blockchain-101-quick-start-guide-for-developers-bluemix-trs/index.html"
                    >IBM Blockchain 101: Quick-start guide for developers</a> to
                experiment with your own blockchain network in a secure cloud environment. </p>
            
            <heading refname="" type="h3">IBM-signed and tested images from Docker
                Hub</heading>
                <p>Alternatively, you can set up and run a blockchain network using IBM-signed
                Docker images and Docker Compose files. The images have been tested for
                functionality, stability, and performance, and you can deploy them in any
                environment you choose. IBM offers technical support for this
                configuration for purchase.</p>
            <p>Get the <a target="new" href="https://hub.docker.com/u/ibmblockchain/"
                    >images on Docker Hub</a>, and <a target="new"
                    href="https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/hyperledger-fabric-support.html"
                    >learn more</a>.</p>

            <heading type="h3">Other offerings</heading>
            <p>IBM offers a high-security environment for enterprise deployments. Networks
                run in isolation on secure infrastructure that prevents any backdoor
                access or tampering.</p>
            <p>IBM also offers the Watson IoT<trade/> Platform with its built-in
                capability for adding selected Internet of Things data to a private
                blockchain. <!-\-an integrated blockchain
                + IOT platform-\->
                This allows IoT devices to send data to private blockchain ledgers for
                inclusion in shared transactions with tamper-resistant records.</p>
            <p>Learn more about <a target="new"
                    href="http://www.ibm.com/blockchain/offerings.html">IBM Blockchain
                    solutions</a>.</p>--><heading refname="" type="h2">Conclusion</heading><p>Blockchain technologies represent a fundamentally new way to transact
                business. They usher in a robust and smart next generation of applications
                for the registry and exchange of physical, virtual, tangible, and
                intangible assets. Thanks to the key concepts of cryptographic security,
                decentralized consensus, and a shared public ledger (with its properly
                controlled and permissioned visibility), blockchain technologies can
                profoundly change the way we organize our economic, social, political, and
                scientific activities.<br/><nbsp/><br/></p><heading type="h2">Next steps</heading><p>We'll conclude this introduction to distributed ledgers with six great
                ways to continue your blockchain odyssey:</p><ul><li>Explore blockchain technology by getting your hands on code! 
                    With the new IBM Blockchain Platform Starter Plan, you can
                    quickly spin up a blockchain pre-production network, deploy sample applications, 
            and develop and deploy client applications. <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-ibm-blockchain-101-quick-start-guide-for-developers-bluemix-trs/index.html"><strong>Get started</strong></a>!<br/><nbsp/><br/></li><li>Stay in the know with the Blockchain Newsletter from developerWorks. Check
                    out the <a href="http://ibm.biz/blockchain-newsletter" target="new"><strong>current issue</strong></a> and <a href="http://ibm.biz/blockchain-newsletter-signup" target="new"><strong>subscribe</strong></a>.<br/><nbsp/><br/></li><li>Stop by the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/blockchain" target="new"><strong>Blockchain Developer Center</strong></a> on
                    developerWorks. It's your source for free tools and tutorials, along
                    with code and community support, for developing and deploying
                    blockchain solutions for business.<br/><nbsp/><br/></li><li>Take the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/courses/all/blockchain-essentials/" target="new"><strong>Blockchain essentials course for
                            developers</strong></a> to learn the ins and outs of asset
                    transfers. At the end of the free, self-paced course, take a quiz, get
                    a badge, and start planning useful blockchain applications for your
                    business network.<br/><nbsp/><br/></li><li>Advance to the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/courses/all/ibm-blockchain-foundation-developer/" target="new"><strong>IBM Blockchain foundation
                            developer course</strong></a>, a free 6-hour course that expands on
                    "Blockchain essentials" and provides a more detailed picture of the
                    components and architecture of blockchain business networks, as well
                    as experience building a network and creating an application.<br/><nbsp/><br/></li><li>Check out the many <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/code/technologies/blockchain/"><strong>blockchain code patterns</strong></a>, which provide roadmaps for solving
                    complex problems, and include overviews, architecture diagrams, process flows, repo pointers, 
                    and additional reading.</li></ul><p><em><strong>This content was originally published on IBM developerWorks on May 9,
                2016.</strong></em></p><!--<heading refname="" type="h4">Acknowledgments</heading>
            <p>The authors are grateful for contributions from Nitin Gaur, Joshua Horton,
                and Nikhil Gupta, who reviewed the content and provided constructive
                suggestions. Additionally, they thank Scott Sloan, Sujatha Perepa, and the
                rest of the IBM Technical Sales Leadership Council (TSLC) team for
                connecting as one unified IBM Blockchain team.</p>
            <p><nbsp/></p>--><!--<related-topics-block>
                <link>
                    <text>IBM Blockchain Platform</text>
                    <url>http://ibm.com/blockchain/platform/</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>IBM Blockchain Platform: Developers</text>
                    <url>https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/getting-started</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Blockchain Developer Center</text>
                    <url>https://developer.ibm.com/blockchain</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Blockchain basics: Glossary and use cases</text>
                    <url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-blockchain-basics-glossary-bluemix-trs/</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Blockchain 101: Quick-start guide for developers</text>
                    <url>http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/cloud/library/cl-ibm-blockchain-101-quick-start-guide-for-developers-bluemix-trs/index.html</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Blockchain essentials (free course for developers)</text>
                    <url>https://developer.ibm.com/courses/all/blockchain-essentials/</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Blockchain solutions and services from IBM</text>
                    <url>https://www.ibm.com/blockchain/offerings.html</url>
                    <!-\-<url>https://console.ng.bluemix.net/catalog/services/blockchain?cm_sp=dw-bluemix-_-cl-blockchain-basics-glossary-bluemix-trs-_-article</url>-\->
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Hyperledger Composer</text>
                    <url>https://hyperledger.org/projects/composer</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Hyperledger Fabric</text>
                    <url>http://hyperledger-fabric.readthedocs.io/en/latest/</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Hyperledger Fabric application samples</text>
                    <url>https://github.com/hyperledger/fabric-samples</url>
                </link>
                <link>
                    <text>Hyperledger community</text>
                    <url>https://www.hyperledger.org/community</url>
                </link>
            </related-topics-block>--></docbody></dw-article><!-- PUB_TO_MAV --></dw-document>