<dw-document xmlns:dw="http://www.ibm.com/developerWorks/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" local-site="worldwide" version="v18" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../schema/dw-document-8.0.xsd"><dw-article auto-number="yes" layout="ArticleStandard18" skill-level="3" toc="yes"><id cma-id="1048324" original="yes"/><keywords content="IoT, architectures, reference architecture, connected devices"/><meta-last-updated day="03" initials="corbinm@us.ibm.com" month="01" year="2018"/><content-area-primary name="iot"/><title>Simplify the development of your IoT solutions with IoT
      architectures</title><subtitle>Strategies for creating scalable, flexible, and robust IoT
      solutions</subtitle><pdf pages="8" paperSize="common" size="362 KB" url="iot-lp201-iot-architectures-pdf.pdf"/><author email="anna.m.gerber@gmail.com" email-cc="" jobtitle="Senior Software Developer" publish-email="no"><author-level>none</author-level><bio>Anna Gerber is a full-stack developer with 15 years experience in the
                university sector, formerly a Technical Project Manager at The University
                of Queensland ITEE eResearch specialising in Digital Humanities, and a
                Research Scientist at the Distributed System Technology Centre (DSTC).
                Anna is a JavaScript robotics enthusiast and maker and enjoys tinkering
                with soft circuits and 3D printers.</bio><img align="left" alt="Anna Gerber" height="60" src="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/p-agerber60.jpg" valign="top" width="60"/><author-name><GivenName>Anna</GivenName><FamilyName>Gerber</FamilyName></author-name><company-name/><social-networks><social-network><social-network-name>dW author profile</social-network-name><social-network-url>https://developer.ibm.com/author/anna.m.gerber/</social-network-url></social-network></social-networks></author><date-published day="07" month="08" year="2017"/><!--<date-updated day="07" month="09" year="2017"/>--><social-media-meta><twitter-summary-card><twitter-card-title>Simplify the development of your IoT solutions with
          IoT architectures: Strategies for creating scalable, flexible, and
          robust IoT solutions</twitter-card-title><twitter-card-abstract>Apply these strategies when you plan data-driven
          IoT architectures. These strategies help you simplify development,
          manage complexity, and ensure that your IoT solutions remain scalable,
          flexible, and robust.</twitter-card-abstract><twitter-card-img height="440" src="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/twitterdw-topic-iot.png" width="880"/></twitter-summary-card></social-media-meta><abstract>Apply these strategies when you plan data-driven IoT
      architectures. These strategies help you simplify development, manage
      complexity, and ensure that your IoT solutions remain scalable, flexible,
      and robust.</abstract><docbody><sidebar><heading>IoT 201: Building skills in IoT development</heading><p>This article is part of the <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/library/iot-lp201-next-steps-guide-iot-developers/index.html" target="_blank">IoT 201 learning path</a>, a next-steps developer
                    guide for IoT.</p><ul><li><a href="https://developer.ibm.com/dwblog/2017/dive-deeper-iot-development/" target="_blank">Diving deeper into IoT development</a></li><li><a href="https://developer.ibm.com/dwblog/2017/5-popular-iot-developer-kits-help-speed-iot-development/" target="_blank">IoT developer kits</a></li><li>IoT architectures (this article)</li><li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp201-iot-connected-cities/index.html" target="_blank">Large-scale IoT solution: Connected
                        cities</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp201-build-skills-iot-health-app/" target="_blank">Tutorial: Develop a healthy habits
                        tracker</a></li></ul></sidebar><p>One of the biggest challenges you face when you are planning Internet
        of Things (IoT) solutions is dealing with complexity. A typical IoT
        solution involves many heterogeneous IoT devices, with sensors that
        produce data that is then analyzed to gain insights. IoT devices are
        connected either directly to a network or through a gateway device to a
        network, which enables the devices to communicate with each other and
        with cloud services and applications (<xref href="#ibmmodel"/>).</p><figure><heading refname="ibmmodel">Human view of Internet of Things (Source:
          X-Force Research and Development, “IBM X-Force Threat Intelligence
          Quarterly 4Q 2014,” Doc # WGL03062USEN, Publish Date: Nov 2014.
          http://www.ibm.com/security/xforce/downloads.html)
          <!--(Source: IBM POV white paper "Internet of Things
          Security" -\- <a
            href="https://www-01.ibm.com/common/ssi/cgi-bin/ssialias?htmlfid=RAW14382USEN"
            >https://www-01.ibm.com/common/ssi/cgi-bin/ssialias?htmlfid=RAW14382USEN</a>;
          although it really came from this slideshare:
          https://www.slideshare.net/patrickbouillaud/wgl03062-usen-copy)--></heading><img alt="" height="787" src="image1.png" width="1057"/></figure><p>Edge <a href="https://www.ibm.com/blogs/internet-of-things/edge-iot-analytics/">computing</a> describes the work that happens at the edges of the IoT
        network, where the physical devices connect to the cloud. With a focus
        on reducing latency, improving privacy, and reducing bandwidth costs
        within data-driven IoT applications, edge computing architectures are
        becoming increasingly common within IoT. </p><p>In this article, I discuss the following strategies that you can apply
        when you plan data-driven IoT architectures. These strategies help you
        simplify development, manage complexity, and ensure that your IoT
        solutions remain scalable, flexible, and robust:</p><ul><li>Adopt a layered architecture</li><li>Security by design</li><li>Automate operations</li><li>Design for interoperability</li><li>Follow a reference architecture</li></ul><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_1" refname="1Adoptalayeredarchitectureoutline" type="h2">Adopt a layered architecture</heading><p>An architecture describes the structure of your IoT solution, including
        the physical aspects (that is, the things) and the virtual aspects (like
        services and communication protocols). Adopting a multi-tiered
        architecture allows you to focus on improving your understanding about
        how all of the most important aspects of the architecture operate
        independently before you integrate them within your IoT application.
        This modular approach helps to manage the complexity of IoT
        solutions.</p><p>For data-driven IoT applications that involve edge analytics, a basic
        three-tiered architecture, which is shown in Figure 2, captures the flow
        of information from devices, to edge services, and then out to cloud
        services. A more detailed IoT architecture would also include vertical
        layers that cut across the other layers, like identity management or
        data security.</p><figure><heading refname="archlayers">Layers of an IoT architecture</heading><!-- ORIG IMG SIZE:  601x513 --><img alt="" height="256" src="image2.png" width="300"/></figure><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_2" refname="13Deviceslayeroutline" type="h3">Devices layer</heading><sidebar><p>You can read more about the IoT device characteristics in my <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-best-hardware-devices-iot-project/index.html" target="_blank">IoT hardware guide</a>.</p><p>You can read more about the network technologies in my <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-connectivity-network-protocols/index.html" target="_blank">IoT connectivity guide</a>.</p></sidebar><p>The components in the device layer (shown at the bottom of <xref href="#archlayers"/>) include physical sensors and actuators that are
        connected to IoT devices and the IoT devices themselves. Sensors and
        actuators on their own are typically not considered to be "smart"
        devices, but sensors and actuators often connect either directly or
        wirelessly over technologies like Bluetooth LE or ZigBee to IoT devices
        that have more processing capabilities. </p><p>Some IoT devices communicate directly with related cloud services and
        apps. However, it is common for IoT devices to communicate upstream
        through gateways, which are intermediate devices that have slightly more
        processing power than the basic IoT devices. Although they don't always
        have sensors attached directly, gateway devices play an important role
        in the data acquisition process. They can perform basic
        analog-to-digital conversions, scaling, and other normalization of the
        raw sensor data readings.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_2" refname="14Edgelayeroutline" type="h3">Edge layer</heading><p>The Edge layer (shown as the middle tier of <xref href="#archlayers"/>)
        relates to the analytics and pre-processing services that are located at
        the edge of the network. Edge analytics occurs in real time (or near
        real time) by processing the stream of data at the point where the data
        is collected as it comes in from the sensors. Basic pre-processing tasks
        like filtering and aggregation of data are performed at the edge, and
        then key pre-processed data is transferred upstream to cloud services
        and applications for further processing and analytics.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_2" refname="15Cloudlayeroutline" type="h3">Cloud layer</heading><p>After the data has been prepared, it is sent upstream for further
        processing, storage, and use within cloud applications, in the cloud
        layer (shown as the top tier of <xref href="#archlayers"/>). The cloud
        applications that perform the data processing are often complemented by
        mobile apps and web-based client applications that present the data to
        end users and that provide access to tools for further exploration and
        analysis through dashboards and visualizations.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_2" refname="2SecuritybyDesignoutline" type="h2">Implement "Security by Design"</heading><sidebar><p>You can read more about security by design in this <a href="https://www-01.ibm.com/common/ssi/cgi-bin/ssialias?htmlfid=RAW14382USEN" target="_blank">IBM Point of View white paper, <em>Internet of
              Things Security</em>.</a></p></sidebar><p>To achieve end-to-end security within an IoT solution, security must be
        a priority across all of the layers of your IoT architecture. You need
        to think about security as a cross-cutting concern in your IoT
        architecture, rather than as a separate layer of your IoT architecture
        to be tackled in isolation at the end. With so many devices connected,
        the integrity of the system as a whole needs to be maintained even when
        individual devices or gateways are compromised. Ensure that your
        architecture supports multiple layers of defense. Also, ensure that your
        IoT solution can identify and neutralize devices that become
        compromised, such as by using gateways to isolate vulnerable devices and
        to monitor communications and usage patterns to detect anomalies.</p><sidebar><p>You can read more about IoT security in <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/security/library/iot-trs-secure-iot-solutions1/index.html" target="_blank">this developerWorks article series</a>.</p></sidebar><p>You should adopt standards and best practices for these aspects of your
        IoT infrastructure: </p><ul><li>Device, application and user identity, authentication,
          authorization, and access control</li><li>Key management</li><li>Data security</li><li>Secure communication channels and message integrity (by using
          encryption)</li><li>Auditing</li><li>Secure development and delivery</li></ul><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_4" refname="4Automateoperationsoutline" type="h2">Automate operations</heading><p>Ensure that your IoT architecture supports automation and orchestration
        across all of the layers. Plan to use these automation features when you
        roll out your IoT solution so that you can support fast and easy
        development and deployment. For example, a microservices architecture at
        the Edge or Cloud Layer can be implemented by using <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/mobile/library/iot-docker-containers/index.html" target="_blank">container technologies</a> and orchestrated by using
        tools such as <a href="https://console.bluemix.net/docs/containers/container_index.html" target="_blank">Kubernetes</a>, provided by your IoT platform. These
        features make operations like setting up a new device or gateway or
        deploying a new instance of a cloud application to process the device
        data less error prone. Avoiding manual configuration ensures that
        operations are repeatable, which is essential for being able to scale up
        to IoT solutions that involve thousands or even millions of connected
        devices.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_5" refname="5DesignforInteroperabilityoutline" type="h2">Design for interoperability</heading><p>The diversity of devices, network protocols, and data formats that you
        adopt in your IoT solutions presents one of the greatest architectural
        challenges for IoT. If you intend to adopt more than one IoT platform in
        your IoT solution, you'll need to consider whether the technologies that
        are used within each IoT platform can be integrated into a cohesive
        solution. </p><p>One of the best strategies for maintaining interoperability in IoT is
        adopting standards. Standards provide you with flexibility to switch out
        or introduce additional components, as long as the new components
        conform to the same standards that you already adopted. </p><p>Reference architectures also provide guidelines to assist you in
        planning your IoT architecture. They are usually standards-based and
        encapsulate design patterns and best practices. Adopting a reference
        architecture, and then selecting IoT platforms that implement them by
        following the guidelines described in the reference architecture, is a
        reliable strategy for maintaining interoperability within your IoT
        architecture.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_6" refname="6Followreferencearchitecturesoutline" type="h2">Follow reference
        architectures</heading><p>There are many initiatives currently working towards standardizing IoT
        architectures to improve interoperability. IoT platform vendors and
        research partners collaborate through these initiatives to define IoT
        reference architectures. Reference architectures act as an architectural
        foundation, describing high level building blocks that are used within
        IoT solutions and establishing a shared terminology for key
        architectural concepts. These initiatives draw on a broad range of
        existing solutions to highlight effective design patterns and best
        practices. </p><p>Some widely referenced IoT reference architectures include:</p><ul><li><a href="http://www.meet-iot.eu/deliverables-IOTA/D1_5.pdf" target="_blank">Internet of Things – Architecture (IoT-A)</a>: The
          IoT-A reference model and architecture was developed through an EU
          lighthouse project in 2013. IoT-A was designed to be built upon in
          order to develop concrete architectures that are applicable across a
          range of domains.</li><li><a href="https://standards.ieee.org/develop/project/2413.html" target="_blank">IEEE P2413 - Standard for an Architectural Framework
            for the Internet of Things (IoT):</a> This ongoing IEEE
          standardization project aims to identify commonalities across IoT
          domains, including manufacturing, smart buildings, smart cities,
          intelligent transport systems, smart grid, and healthcare.</li><li><a href="https://www.iiconsortium.org/IIC_PUB_G1_V1.80_2017-01-31.pdf?cm_mc_uid=42240287207114889661528&amp;cm_mc_sid_50200000=1498959849" target="_blank">Industrial Internet Reference Architecture
            (IIRA)</a> – IIRA was developed specifically for industrial IoT
          applications by the Industrial Internet Consortium, which was founded
          in March 2014 by AT&amp;T, Cisco, General Electric, IBM, and
          Intel.</li></ul><p>Reference architectures can be used as a template for developing IoT
        solutions. The architectures listed above describe IoT architectural
        components and their functions in high-level terms, but they can be made
        more concrete by mapping abstract requirements onto specific
        technologies or technology stacks.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_7" refname="61ComponentsofanIoTReferenceArchitectureoutline" type="h3">Components of an IoT Reference
        Architecture</heading><p>The details of reference architectures differ depending on the
        application domain; however, most IoT reference architectures describe
        at least the following capabilities:</p><ul><li>Managing devices and their data</li><li>Connectivity and communication </li><li>Analytics and applications</li></ul><p>In addition, reference architectures usually also describe mechanisms
        to address non-functional requirements such as flexibility, reliability,
        quality of service, interoperability, and integration.</p><heading alttoc="" refname="611Managingdevicesandtheirdataoutline" type="h4">Managing devices and their data</heading><p>The device management aspect of a reference architecture is concerned
        with managing devices, their identity, and their lifecycles. Reference
        architectures describe: </p><ul><li>Device onboarding </li><li>Updating device firmware </li><li>Applying new configurations </li><li>Triggering remote operations like disabling, enabling, or
          decommissioning devices</li></ul><heading alttoc="" refname="612Connectivityandcommunicationoutline" type="h4">Connectivity and communication</heading><p>Managing connectivity and bidirectional communication between devices,
        between devices and gateways, and between gateways and cloud services
        and applications is another key capability that is often described
        within IoT reference architectures. For edge computing, event-driven
        architectures are a good choice, with communication between devices and
        services using publish/subscribe protocols and message brokers.</p><heading alttoc="" refname="613Analyticsandapplicationsoutline" type="h4">Analytics and applications</heading><p>To derive value from the data that comes from IoT devices, cloud
        applications provide visualization and analytics tools that operate over
        streams or batches of data to identify actionable insights. Depending on
        the use case, decision management and business process tools can trigger
        alerts or carry out actions in response.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_7" refname="62ConcreteReferenceArchitecturesoutline" type="h3">Concrete Reference
        Architectures</heading><p>The patterns and guidelines that are often provided by a reference
        architecture can be drawn from within a specific IoT domain, such as
        Industrial IoT, or can be generalized from solutions across a range of
        domains. High-level generalized architectures can be used as templates
        to create more concrete domain-specific or platform-specific
        architectures. </p><sidebar><p>You can read more about IoT platforms in my <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-why-use-iot-platform/index.html" target="_blank">IoT platform guide</a>.</p></sidebar><p>General-purpose IoT platform vendors often provide more applied
        reference architectures, along with implementation guides for developing
        IoT solutions that conform to their reference architectures using the
        tools and software agents that are provided by the platform. Some IoT
        platform-centric reference architectures include:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/devops/method/content/architecture/iotArchitecture" target="_blank">IBM IoT reference architecture </a></li><li><a href="https://www.intel.com.au/content/www/au/en/internet-of-things/white-papers/iot-platform-reference-architecture-paper.html" target="_blank">Intel IoT platform Reference Architecture </a></li><li><a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-au/updates/microsoft-azure-iot-reference-architecture-available/" target="_blank">Microsoft Azure IoT Architecture</a></li><li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/startups/iot-a-small-things-primer/" target="_blank">Amazon Web Services Pragma Architecture</a></li></ul><p><a href="https://www.ibm.com/devops/method/content/architecture/iotArchitecture/industrie_40" target="_blank">IBM Industrie 4.0</a> reference architecture is an
        example of a domain-specific reference architecture, which is designed
        for industrial IoT applications, based on the IIRA reference
        architecture and the IBM IoT Reference Architecture. </p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_7" refname="7Conclusionoutline" type="h2">Conclusion</heading><p>Designing data-driven IoT solutions is complex due to the scale and
        heterogeneousness of the devices and connectivity involved. In this
        article, I've outlined some strategies for designing secure, flexible,
        and scalable IoT architectures.</p><related-topics-block><link><text>IoT hardware guide</text><url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-best-hardware-devices-iot-project/index.html</url></link><link><text>IoT connectivity guide</text><url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-connectivity-network-protocols/index.html</url></link><link><text>IoT platforms guide</text><url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-why-use-iot-platform/index.html</url></link><link><text>IBM Point of View white paper, Internet of Things Security</text><url>https://www-01.ibm.com/common/ssi/cgi-bin/ssialias?htmlfid=RAW14382USEN</url></link></related-topics-block></docbody></dw-article><!-- PUB_TO_MAV --></dw-document>