<dw-document xmlns:dw="http://www.ibm.com/developerWorks/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" local-site="worldwide" version="v18" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../schema/dw-document-8.0.xsd"><dw-article auto-number="yes" layout="ArticleStandard18" skill-level="3" toc="yes"><id cma-id="1046519" original="yes"/><keywords content="IoT, IoT platforms"/><meta-last-updated day="12" initials="corbinm@us.ibm.com" month="02" year="2018"/><content-area-primary name="iot"/><title>Streamlining the development of your IoT applications by using an IoT
            platform</title><subtitle>A guide to help you understand why you should you use an IoT
            Platform</subtitle><pdf pages="6" paperSize="common" size="141 KB" url="iot-lp101-why-use-iot-platform-pdf.pdf"/><author email="anna.m.gerber@gmail.com" email-cc="troy@backstopmedia.com" jobtitle="Senior Software Developer" publish-email="no"><author-level>none</author-level><bio>Anna Gerber is a full-stack developer with 15 years experience in the
                university sector, formerly a Technical Project Manager at The University
                of Queensland ITEE eResearch specialising in Digital Humanities, and a
                Research Scientist at the Distributed System Technology Centre (DSTC).
                Anna is a JavaScript robotics enthusiast and maker and enjoys tinkering
                with soft circuits and 3D printers.</bio><img align="left" alt="Anna Gerber" height="60" src="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/p-agerber60.jpg" valign="top" width="60"/><author-name><GivenName>Anna</GivenName><FamilyName>Gerber</FamilyName></author-name><company-name/><social-networks><social-network><social-network-name>dW author profile</social-network-name><social-network-url>https://developer.ibm.com/author/anna.m.gerber/</social-network-url></social-network></social-networks></author><date-published day="05" month="06" year="2017"/><date-updated day="03" month="01" year="2018"/><social-media-meta><twitter-summary-card><twitter-card-abstract>This article explores the key capabilities of IoT
                    platforms and considers the top general-purpose end-to-end IoT
                    platforms. You'll learn why you should adopt an IoT platform to
                    rapidly develop your IoT solutions and quickly get the most value from
                    your IoT data.</twitter-card-abstract><twitter-card-img height="440" src="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/i/twitterdw-topic-iot.png" width="880"/></twitter-summary-card></social-media-meta><abstract>This article explores the key capabilities of IoT platforms and
            considers the top general-purpose end-to-end IoT platforms. You'll learn why
            you should adopt an IoT platform to rapidly develop your IoT solutions and
            quickly get the most value from your IoT data.</abstract><docbody><sidebar><heading>IoT 101: Getting started with IoT development</heading><p>This article is part of the <a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-quick-start-guide-iot-developers/index.html" target="_blank">IoT 101 learning path</a>, a quick-start guide
                    for IoT developers.</p><ul><li><a href="https://developer.ibm.com/dwblog/2017/just-getting-started-iot-consider-7-key-iot-concepts-skills/" target="_blank">IoT concepts and skills</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-best-hardware-devices-iot-project/index.html" target="_blank">IoT hardware guide</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-connectivity-network-protocols/index.html" target="_blank">IoT networking guide</a></li><li>IoT platforms (this article)</li><li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-get-started-develop-iot-home-automation/index.html" target="_blank">Tutorial: Build a simple home automation system</a></li></ul></sidebar><p>Developing and deploying IoT systems is complex<mdash/>it involves
                coordinating a diverse range of connected devices, networks, cloud
                services, and mobile and web applications. </p><p>IoT platforms provide middleware to connect and manage hardware devices and
                the data that they collect with user-facing mobile and web applications.
                These IoT platforms are typically designed to establish secure
                communication between devices, apps, and services. They also make it
                faster and easier to develop and deploy IoT applications. IoT platforms
                are designed to be scalable and reliable. For example, they implement
                fault tolerance so that your IoT systems will continue to operate in the
                face of device, network, or cloud service failures. By leveraging
                standards and providing well documented APIs and SDKs, IoT platforms
                enable you to integrate heterogeneous devices, apps, and services into
                your IoT system, providing you with the flexibility to customize and
                substitute components as requirements change. </p><p>The Internet of Things is evolving at a rapid pace, so you'll need to
                develop your IoT applications quickly and efficiently to minimize time to
                market and remain competitive. Although each IoT initiative comes with its
                own set of unique requirements, most IoT projects share some common
                requirements for the management of connected devices and the
                communication, storage, and analysis of the data that they generate. IoT
                platforms address these fundamental requirements by providing generic,
                customizable tools and services and also the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/iotplatform/2017/01/17/iot-platform-vs-iot-infrastructure/">abstractions</a> that you can build upon when you develop your custom
                IoT solutions. </p><p>By exploring the key capabilities of IoT platforms and considering the top
                general-purpose end-to-end IoT platforms, you will come to realize why you
                should adopt an IoT platform to rapidly develop your IoT solutions and
                quickly get the most value from your IoT data.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_2" refname="2IoTplatformcapabilitiesoutline" type="h2">IoT platform capabilities</heading><p>Consider these key IoT platform capabilities: </p><ul><li>Device management</li><li>Data communication protocols</li><li>Data storage </li><li>Rules and analytics</li><li>Rapid application development and deployment</li><li>Integration </li><li>Security </li><li>Cost of developing and maintaining the solutions that you build with
                    the IoT platform. </li></ul><p>The relative importance of each of these capabilities will depend on your
                use case. For example, consider a small-scale home automation system.
                Device management is not a primary concern because there are so few
                devices to manage. Because a home automation use case is a fairly reactive
                use case, it is less important that the IoT platform provide data storage
                and data analytics capabilities to store and analyze historical sensor
                readings. However, the IoT platform must support fast and reliable data
                communication protocols to ensure that events that are detected by sensors
                are not missed and can be responded to in near real time. And yet, for an
                industrial IoT application that involves thousands of sensors that monitor
                factory equipment in order to detect equipment failures and to predict
                when to perform maintenance on the equipment, the device management and
                analytics capabilities of the IoT platform would obviously be much more
                important.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="21Devicemanagementoutline" type="h3">Device management</heading><sidebar><p>Read more about managing IoT devices in my developerWorks article, "<a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-best-hardware-devices-iot-project/index.html">Choosing the best hardware for your next IoT project</a>."</p></sidebar><p>One of the core functions of an IoT platform is managing IoT hardware
                devices. Device management occurs throughout the entire lifecycle of each
                IoT device, including provisioning of new devices, monitoring and
                maintaining operating devices, and eventually decommissioning devices when
                they reach their end of life. IoT platforms provide features for managing
                device registration, configuration, and over-the-air updates. With an IoT
                Platform, you can receive alerts for the device status and monitor
                statistics for the device health or usage. IoT Platforms also provide
                remote debugging for when things go wrong. Asset management, including the
                ability to list and search connected devices and to query and manage
                device metadata, also falls under the umbrella of device management. </p><p>Look for IoT platforms that are device agnostic and that can integrate with
                your existing Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) systems.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="22Datacommunicationprotocolsoutline" type="h3">Data communication protocols</heading><sidebar><p>Read more about IoT networking protocols in my developerWorks article,
                        "<a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-connectivity-network-protocols/index.html">Connecting all the things in the Internet of Things</a>."</p></sidebar><p>Secure and reliable communication between IoT devices, gateways, and
                cloud-based apps and services is essential for enabling remote management
                and updating the connected devices as well as for the transmission of
                data. Although some data can be stored and processed locally with edge
                analytics, some of the data that is collected from sensors and other IoT
                devices will need to be delivered to cloud services or apps upstream for
                aggregation, further processing, or visualization. Because thousands of
                devices are often connected within a single IoT system, many IoT platforms
                incorporate message broker services to enable devices and gateways to send
                and receive messages with low latency and at scale. These message broker
                services usually use standard communication protocols like MQTT, CoAP, or
                XMPP. Some platforms also support web sockets for real-time
                communication.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="23Datastorageoutline" type="h3">Data storage</heading><p>With billions of connected devices generating data at an unprecedented
                rate, where to store the vast quantities of data is another aspect to
                consider when you are choosing an IoT platform. Data lakes are used to
                store data in a variety of formats including raw, structured,
                semi-structured, or structured. These data lakes are often built on top of
                NoSQL or Hadoop technologies for maximum flexibility and scalability. Data
                lakes and other data stores provided by IoT platforms are usually highly
                available, support concurrent reads and writes, and include configurable
                indexes to improve performance when your IoT app accesses and queries the
                data. </p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="24RulesandAnalyticsoutline" type="h3">Rules and Analytics</heading><p>Once the data is reliably stored, the next consideration is how to gain
                insight from your IoT data. Many IoT platforms offer analytics
                capabilities that include real-time and batch processing. A rules engine
                demonstrates the power of real-time data analytics to produce actionable
                insights, with rules encoding the conditions that are used to trigger
                actions. Some platforms provide turnkey analytics applications, however a
                platform that supports customization of built-in reports, analytics
                dashboards, and data visualizations is an even more flexible choice.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="25Rapidapplicationdevelopmentanddeploymentoutline" type="h3">Rapid application development and
                deployment</heading><p>Speeding up development and delivery of purpose-built applications is one
                of the main motivating factors for adopting an IoT platform. So, it makes
                sense to select an IoT platform that provides code boilerplate generation
                tools, templates or widgets to support rapid development, and tools to
                streamline and automate deployment. </p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="26Integrationoutline" type="h3">Integration</heading><p>Interoperability is an important consideration within IoT because of the
                huge variety of connected devices and IoT-related services already in
                production, not to mention the billions more that are anticipated to come
                online in the coming years. With IoT evolving so quickly, future-proofing
                your IoT system is essential. IoT platforms achieve this interoperability
                by adopting standards and by providing additional layers of abstraction
                and normalization over the underlying technologies. For example, your
                applications are less likely to break when things change, if you upgrade
                your IoT devices to use a sensor with a higher resolution. IoT platforms
                provide integration with other platforms, devices, web services, tools,
                and applications through SDKs and APIs, with REST APIs being particularly
                common.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="27Securityoutline" type="h3">Security</heading><p>Security is an integral part of the design of any IoT solution. Security
                includes securing devices and network communication in addition to
                implementing cloud and application-level security. Choose an IoT platform
                that provides authentication and authorization services, preferably with
                integration to existing systems that are used for identity management like
                LDAP, and one that adopts standards, like X.509 for device authentication.
                For secure communication, your IoT platform should adopt a standard like
                TLS for encrypting content and ensuring data integrity. IoT platforms
                might also implement role-based access control for users, devices,
                gateways, and services, as well as providing security monitoring and
                auditing tools.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="28Costoutline" type="h3">Cost</heading><p>Speeding up development of IoT solutions is one of the main benefits of
                adopting an IoT platform, however an IoT platform can also help to reduce
                development costs. Ongoing costs, like subscription fees for accessing a
                hosted IoT platform or hosting costs for a self-hosted platform, will
                typically be less than the cost of developing and maintaining custom-made
                in-house solutions. Many IoT platforms offer free trial periods or low
                usage tiers that you can use to get started with almost no upfront
                expenditure, but be sure to factor in how those costs will change after
                the initial trial is over.</p><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_3" refname="3ComparingIoTplatformsoutline" type="h2">Comparing IoT platforms</heading><p>There are hundreds of IoT platforms available from a range of vendors. Some
                platforms are highly specialized, for example, only catering to one market
                vertical like GE Predix (<a href="https://www.predix.io/)">https://www.predix.io/)</a>, a PaaS IoT platform aimed specifically
                at Industrial IoT. Other IoT platforms are focused on providing only a
                subset of the functions that might be required for your IoT system, rather
                than an end-to-end IoT platform solution, for example, Cisco and SAS
                Edge-to-Enterprise IoT Analytics Platform, which is focused on IoT
                analytics only. As a result, you might choose to adopt more than one IoT
                platform.</p><p>As a starting point, here are five popular general-purpose end-to-end IoT
                platforms that are suitable for a wide range of applications: </p><ul><li><strong><a href="https://www.ibm.com/internet-of-things/platform/watson-iot-platform/">IBM Watson IoT</a></strong><sidebar><p>Want to give Watson IoT Platform a try?  Create your Internet of
                        Things application with Watson IoT Platform at no charge with your
                    <a href="https://www.ibm.com/internet-of-things/spotlight/watson-iot-platform/trial"><strong>free trial</strong></a>.</p></sidebar><p>Built on top of the IBM Cloud platform, IBM Watson IoT is a
                        mature, developer-friendly IoT platform with strengths in
                        real-time analytics and cognitive computing.</p><p>The platform also supports device management, authentication and
                        authorization, secure data storage and communication, standard
                        communication protocols like MQTT and HTTPS, rules, REST APIs and
                        SDKs. According to the IDC, a market research company, the <a href="https://www.ibmjournal.com/internet-of-things/ibm-watson-iot-platform-could-be-the-platform-of-platforms">Watson IoT portfolio and the Watson IoT Platform were named
                            the IoT Platform of Platforms</a>.</p></li><li><strong><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/iot-platform/how-it-works/">Amazon Web Services IoT</a></strong><p>AWS IoT is a highly scalable IoT platform. It includes an SDK,
                        authentication and authorization, device registry, a device
                        gateway that communicates with devices using MQTT, WebSockets or
                        HTTP, and a rules engine that integrates with existing AWS
                        services like DynamoDB. An interesting feature of AWS IoT is
                        "device shadows," which is a persistent virtual version of each
                        device including the last known state of the device.</p></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-au/internet-of-things/azure-iot-suite">Microsoft Azure IoT Suite</a></strong><p>The Microsoft Azure IoT Suite is another comprehensive IoT
                        platform, which includes support for device management and device
                        twins (like device shadowing) by using Azure IoT Hub, standard
                        communication protocols including MQTT, AMQP, and HTTP, secure
                        storage, rules, and analytics engines supporting predictive
                        analysis and data visualization.</p></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.thingworx.com/">ThingWorx</a></strong><p>PTC ThingWorx is an enterprise IoT platform that supports
                        model-driven rapid application development. Features include
                        device management, application modeling, support for standard
                        protocols including MQTT, AMQP, XMPP, CoAP, and WebSockets and
                        predictive analytics, as well as REST APIs and SDKs to support
                        integration.</p></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.kaaproject.org/">Kaa</a></strong><p>Kaa
                        is a free open source IoT platform that is published under an
                        Apache 2.0 license, which allows the platform to be self-hosted.
                        Kaa includes REST APIs and SDKs for Java, C++, and C, with
                        features for device management, data collection, configuration
                        management, notifications, load balancing, and data analysis.</p></li></ul><heading alttoc="" inline-commenting-id="cmt_4" refname="4Summaryoutline" type="h2">Summary</heading><p>With so many different IoT platforms to choose from, selecting a platform
                may seem daunting at first. Consider your requirements against the
                capabilities of each platform to select the best match for your business.
                Adopting an IoT platform can simplify, speed up, and otherwise streamline
                the development of your next IoT project. By using an IoT platform, you
                can focus on the requirements that are unique to your use-case and quickly
                deliver value to your customers.</p><related-topics-block><link><text>IoT Platform versus IoT Infrastructure</text><url>https://developer.ibm.com/iotplatform/2017/01/17/iot-platform-vs-iot-infrastructure/</url></link><link><text>Watson IoT Platform Developer Center</text><url>https://developer.ibm.com/iotplatform/</url></link><link><text>Connecting all the things in the Internet of Things</text><url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-connectivity-network-protocols/index.html</url></link><link><text>Choosing the best hardware for your next IoT project</text><url>https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/iot-lp101-best-hardware-devices-iot-project/index.html</url></link></related-topics-block></docbody></dw-article><!-- PUB_TO_MAV --></dw-document>